Guide to the Peter Palmquist Cased Photographs Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Identified Subjects by Unidentified Photographers, 1850-60; Series II; (26 items)
  - Miller, Jack
    - Daguerreotype in a case, of a man, identified as Jack Miller, 1851 (Box 19, Folder 182)
      Placerville, California, or Jackson, California
      Full leather case with Maiden Scattering Roses motif (Rinhart #120)
      Inscription behind image, "Jack Miller / Placer[ville], CA / and Jackson, Calif. 1851"
  - Showalter, Daniel (circa 1829-1866)
    - Ambrotype in a case, of an unidentified Native American or Chicano man, and a man identified as Dan Showalter, circa 1860 (Box 19, Folder 183)
      Quarter-plate clear-glass ambrotype; no seal
      Full leather case with jewel medallion motif
      Daniel Showalter was a member of California state assembly, representing the 6th District, Mariposa County, 1857-58, 1861-62, and a pro-Confederate secessionist during the Civil War. The unidentified Native American or Chicano man is also depicted in Items 198 and 199
  - Smith, Ben
    - Daguerreotype in a case, of a man, identified as Ben Smith, circa 1852 (Box 19, Folder 184)
      Sixth-plate daguerreotype; masking-tape seal
      Inscription on paper accompanying the item, "Ben Smith / Cala."
  - Wagener, Francis Otto (b. 1827), Francis Uslar, and Fred Nancki
    - Daguerreotype in a case, of three men, man in center identified as Francis Otto Wagener, others identified as Francis Uslar and Fred Nancki, 1855 Mar 28 (Box 19, Folder 185)
      San Francisco, California
      Full black pigskin case with lion and unicorn crest and motto motif
      Inscription in a case, behind images, "Dear Daddy and his Friends / Taken / on the 28th of March / 1855 / Francis Uslar / born on the 28th of [December] / Fred Nancki / (center picture) / our dear Daddy / Francis Otto Wagener / taken 28th March 1855 / born April 15, 1827 / age 28 years"
  - Wightman family
    - Daguerreotype not in a case, of a woman, identified as Gertrude Wightman, circa 1855-60 (Box 19, Folder 186)
      Inscription on verso, "Grandma Wightman / Aunt Gertrude"
    - Daguerreotype not in a case, of a man, identified as Mr. Wightman, circa 1855-60 (Box 19, Folder 187)
      Inscription on verso, "Grandpa Wightman"
- Identified Places by Unidentified Photographers, Series III; (132 items)
  Series III, Identified Places by Unidentified Photographers, is arranged geographically by identified and unidentified locations in California, followed by identified locations in Iowa, New York, and the New England region.
  - Eureka, California, or Trinidad, California
    - Ambrotype in a case, of an exterior, man on horseback and five men standing on steps of a wooden building, circa 1857 (Box 19, Folder 188)
      Quarter-plate ambrotype
  - San Francisco, California
    - Daguerreotype in a case, of a man, circa 1852-53 (Box 19, Folder 189)
  - California
    - Daguerreotype in a case, of a woman, circa 1852-55 (Box 19, Folder 190)
    - Four daguerreotypes in a false watch case, each depicting a single child, consisting of three girls and a boy, 1853 (Box 20, Folder 191)
      Four 3 cm. diameter circle plate daguerreotypes
      Gold false watch case; cover of watch inscribed with scene of coastal town with ships, mountains and church; back cover of case inscribed, "E.S. Wood / 1853"
    - Wet collodion process on cloth, not in a case, of an infant, circa 1856 (Box 20, Folder 192)
      Ninth-plate wet collodion process on cloth
    - Wet collodion process on leather, not in a case, of a man, circa 1856 (Box 20, Folder 193)
    - Wet collodion process on cloth, not in a case, of a man, circa 1856 (Box 20, Folder 194)
    - Wet collodion process on cloth, with no case, of a man and two boys, circa 1856 (Box 20, Folder 195)
      Sixth-plate wet collodion process on cloth
      Individuals probably family members with individuals in Item 196
    - Wet collodion process on cloth, with no case, of an infant, girl, and woman, circa 1856 (Box 20, Folder 196)
    - Daguerreotype with a horizontal orientation in a case, of an infant, woman, and man, circa 1857 (Box 20, Folder 197)
      Sixth-plate daguerreotype; partial seal
      Full brown leather case with the Hovering Bird, Variant motif (Rinhart #95)
    - Ambrotype in a half case of a man, probably of Chicano or Native American ancestry, circa 1860 (Box 20, Folder 198)
      Sixth-plate clear-glass ambrotype with black paper backing; no seal
      Image probably related to Items 183 and 199
    - Ambrotype in a case of a man, probably of Chicano or Native American ancestry, circa 1860 (Box 20, Folder 199)
      Ninth-plate clear-glass ambrotype with asphaltum backing; cracked plate; no seal
      Full leather case with scalloped floral motif
      Image probably related to Items 183 and 198
    - Tintype in a case of a nude girl, circa 1860 (Box 20, Folder 200)
      Dealer description claims subject is the daughter of the photographer
  - La Moille, Iowa
    - Daguerreotype in a case, of two men, circa 1850 (Box 21, Folder 201)
      Quarter-plate daguerreotype, modern seal
      Full papier-mache case; pencil inscription under velvet pad of case cover, "Lamoille (sic.), Marshall Co., Iowa"
  - Niagara Falls, New York
    - Ambrotype with a horizontal orientation in a case, of an exterior image of two women in front of the Niagara Falls, circa 1857-58 (Box 48, Folder 202)
      Whole-plate clear-glass ambrotype with asphaltum backing; no cover glass
      Full black leather case with geometric and scroll motif
  - New England Region
    Probably Maine and Massachusetts
    - Twenty-seven ambrotypes, each depicting a single individual woman or man, consisting of fifteen women and twelve men, circa 1858
      Twenty-seven ninth-plate ambrotypes in mat
      Display case frame constructed of walnut wood with a red velvet matrix
      Images created by different unidentified photographers
      Representative advertising card, "L. H. LEZZOTT, / AMBROTYPE ARTIST / WINTHROP, ME."
      - Ambrotypes (Box 22, Folder 203a-203i)
      - Ambrotypes (Box 23, Folder 203j-203r)
      - Ambrotypes (Box 24, Folder 203s-203aa)
- Unidentified Subjects by Unidentified Photographers, 1840-69; Series IV; (16 items)
  Series IV, Unidentified Subjects by Unidentified Photographers, is organized into four subseries: Single Individuals, Couples, Groups (images which consist of three or more people), and Objects.
  Items depicting Single Individuals are arranged under headings for Infants, Girls, Boys, Women, and Men. Items depicting Couples are arranged under headings for Infant and Adult, Children, Child and Adult, Women, Men, and Woman and Man. Items are chronologically arranged under each heading.
  Items with two or more plates in a case have been arranged according to the age or gender of the individual that comes first in the organization scheme of this series.
  - SINGLE INDIVIDUALS
    - Infants
      - Daguerreotype in a case, of an infant, circa 1850-55 (Box 21, Folder 204)
        Sixteenth-plate daguerreotype, modern seal
        Full brown pigskin case; inscription under image, "taken when 8 months old"
      - Daguerreotype in a case, of an infant, circa 1850 (Box 21, Folder 205)
        Sixth-plate hand-tinted daguerreotype
      - Ambrotype not in a case, of an infant, circa 1854 (Box 21, Folder 206)
        Inscription on paper label on cover glass, "MY SISTER MYRAETTE"
      - Ambrotype in a frame, of an infant, circa 1855 (Box 49, Folder 207)
        Sixth-plate clear-glass ambrotype with black velvet backing; no seal
        Thermoplastic frame molded in the shape of four intersecting logs with indented green leaves; stamped on plastic back, "PATENTED/ AUG. 7, 1855"
    - Girls
      - Daguerreotype in a case, of a girl, circa 1845-1849 (Box 21, Folder 208)
        Full papier-mache case with Variant of the Crocket Theme (Rinhart #162)
      - Ambrotype in a case, of a girl, circa 1855 (Box 21, Folder 209)
        Sixth-plate clear-glass ambrotype with asphaltum backing; no seal
        Full papier-mache case with small floral bouquet medallion in center
      - Ambrotype in a case, of a girl, circa 1855-60 (Box 21, Folder 210)
        Sixth-plate ambrotype; original seal
        Full brown plain case
        Labels affixed to glass, "$115" and "S. Mortimer Shiner"
      - Ambrotype in a case, of a girl, circa 1856 (Box 25, Folder 211)
        Full leather case with brown velvet cover
      - Ambrotype in a case, of a girl with a cast or lazy eye, circa 1856 (Box 25, Folder 212)
        Sixth-plate clear-glass ambrotype; no seal
        Full papier-mache case with a floral medallion motif
      - Daguerreotype in a case, of a girl, circa 1856-58 (Box 25, Folder 213)
      - Ambrotype in a case, of a girl, circa 1858 (Box 25, Folder 214)
        Ninth-plate clear-glass ambrotype with modern card backing; no seal
        Full leather envelope style case
      - Tintype in a case, of a postmortem girl, circa 1858 (Box 25, Folder 215)
        Sixth-plate ferrotype; unsealed
        Full thermoplastic case with Bluebells in Oval motif (Krainik #196), and the back of case, the Faithful Hound motif (Krainik #142); printed on paper lining, "Littlefield, Parson & Co., / MANUFACTURERS OF / Daguerreotype Cases. / L., P. & Co., are the sole / Proprietors and only legal Manu- / facturers of UNION CASES, with the / Embracing Riveted Hinge, / Patented October 14, 1856, / and April 21, 1857."
      - Collodion on opaque white glass in case, of a girl, circa 1859 (Box 25, Folder 216)
        Sixth-plate oval collodion on opaque white glass; no seal
        Full violet velvet oval case
      - Ambrotype not in a case, of a girl, circa 1860 (Box 25, Folder 217)
        Sixth-plate clear-glass ambrotype with asphaltum/varnish backing; no seal
      - Ambrotype in a case, of a girl, circa 1860 (Box 25, Folder 218)
      - Tintype not in a case, of a girl, circa 1860 (Box 25, Folder 219)
        Ninth-plate tintype; unsealed
        Blindstamp on left side of mat, "HOLMES, BOOTH & HAYDEN SUPERFINE", and a blindstamp on right side of mat, "WATERBURY CONN. No. 49"
      - Tintype not in a case, of a girl, circa 1860-65 (Box 25, Folder 220)
      - Tintype not in a case, of a girl, circa 1864 (Box 26, Folder 221)
        Mat with Constitution and Union motif; stamp on upper edge of mat, "SCOVILL SUPERIOR"
        Image set upside down in mat
    - Boys
      - Ambrotype in a case, of a boy, circa 1860 (Box 26, Folder 222)
        Quarter-plate ruby-glass ambrotype; no seal
        Full black lacquer case with mother-of-pearl inlay and "MEMORIAL" stamped on spine in gold leaf
      - Tintype in a case, of a boy, circa 1855-1859 (Box 26, Folder 223)
        3 cm. diameter, tintype; unsealed
        Full round thermoplastic case with twist-off cover and Geometric motif (Krainik #734)
    - Women
      - Daguerreotype in a case, of a woman, circa 1840-49 (Box 26, Folder 224)
      - Daguerreotype in a case, of a woman, circa 1846-49 (Box 26, Folder 225)
        Quarter-plate daguerreotype; unsealed
        Full pigskin case
      - Daguerreotype in a case, of a woman, circa 1850 (Box 26, Folder 226)
        Full brown leather case with Two Lilies motif (Rinhart #112)
      - Daguerreotype in a case, of a woman, circa 1850 (Box 26, Folder 227)
      - Daguerreotype in a case, of a woman, circa 1850-59 (Box 26, Folder 228)
        Full leather case with Thistle motif (Rinhart #119)
      - Daguerreotype in a case, of a woman, circa 1850-59 (Box 26, Folder 229)
        Sixteenth-plate daguerreotype; unsealed
        Full papier-mache case with geometric motif
      - Daguerreotype in a case, of a woman, circa 1850-59 (Box 26, Folder 230)
        Full brown leather case with Bird and Snake motif (Rinhart #96)
      - Daguerreotype not in a case, of a woman, circa 1850-59 (Box 27, Folder 231)
      - Daguerreotype in a case, of a woman, circa 1850-59 (Box 27, Folder 232)
        Full brown thermoplastic case with the Farmer's Dream motif (Krainik #138)
      - Daguerreotype in a half case, of a woman, circa 1854 (Box 27, Folder 233)
      - Daguerreotype not in a case, of a woman, circa 1854 (Box 27, Folder 234)
        Sixteenth-plate daguerreotype; no seal
      - Ambrotype in a case, of a woman, circa 1855 (Box 27, Folder 235)
        Sixth-plate hand-tinted clear-glass ambrotype with asphaltum/varnish backing; no seal
        Full brown leather case with geometric motif
      - Two tintypes in a case, one depicts a woman, and the other a man, circa 1855 (Box 27, Folder 236)
        4 cm. diameter tintypes
        False gold watch double image case
      - Ambrotype not in a case, of a woman, circa 1855-60 (Box 50, Folder 237)
      - Ambrotype not in a case, of a woman, circa 1855-60 (Box 27, Folder 238)
      - Ambrotype in a half case, of a woman, circa 1856 (Box 27, Folder 239)
        Sixth-plate ruby-glass ambrotype; sealed
      - Ambrotype in a case, of a woman, circa 1856 (Box 27, Folder 240)
        Ninth-plate clear-glass ambrotype with metal backing; original seal
        Full black thermoplastic case with the Church Window motif (Krainik #396); printed in paper backing: "A.P. CRITCHLOW & CO., / Manufacturers of / Daguerreotype Cases. / A.P.C. & CO. / Are the Original Inventors of / the Composition for the Union Case, / (so called,) including all the various shades / of color and fineness of texture pecu- / liar to their manufacture and of the / EMBRACING RIVETED HINGES, thus / securing them from breaking out as / do others that are inserted / with or without a / metal brace. / Hinge Patented / OCT. 14, 1856."
      - Tintype in an oval case, of a woman, circa 1858 (Box 28, Folder 241)
        Ninth-plate oval tintype; unsealed
        Full black oval thermoplastic case with a Rose motif (Krainik #681); printed on paper lining, "Littlefield, Parson & Co., / MANUFACTURERS OF / Daguerreotype Cases. / L., P. & Co., are the sole / Proprietors and only legal Manu- / facturers of UNION CASES, with the / Embracing Riveted Hinge, / Patented October 14, 1856, / and April 21, 1857."
      - Tintype in a case, of a woman, circa 1858 (Box 28, Folder 242)
        Full black and brown leather case with mother-of-pearl inlay
      - Ambrotype in a case, of a woman, circa 1858 (Box 28, Folder 243)
        Ninth-plate ruby-glass ambrotype; no seal
        Full leather envelope-style case
      - Two ambrotypes in a case, one depicts a woman, and the other a man, circa 1858 (Box 28, Folder 244)
        Ninth-plate clear-glass ambrotypes with asphaltum/varnish backing; original seal
        Full double-image leather envelope-style case
      - Collodion on opaque white glass, in a case, of a woman, circa 1859 (Box 28, Folder 245)
        Ninth-plate oval, hand-tinted collodion on opaque white glass
        Full maroon velvet oval case
      - Collodion on opaque white glass, not in case, of a woman, circa 1859 (Box 51, Folder 246)
        Whole-plate hand-tinted collodion on opaque white glass
      - Ambrotype in a case, of a woman, circa 1860 (Box 28, Folder 247)
        Sixteenth-plate clear-glass ambrotype with asphaltum backing; no seal
        Full thermoplastic case with a Indian Profile motif (Krainik #617)
      - Ambrotype in a case, of a woman, circa 1860 (Box 28, Folder 248)
        Quarter-plate clear-glass ambrotype with asphaltum backing; no seal
        Full leather case with vase of flowers motif with the case design stamped upside down
      - Ambrotype not in a case, of a woman, circa 1860 (Box 28, Folder 249)
        Ninth-plate ruby-glass ambrotype; original seal
      - Ambrotype in a case, of a woman, circa 1860 (Box 28, Folder 250)
        Ninth-plate clear-glass ambrotype backed with blackened metal plate; no seal
      - Tintype in a case, of a woman holding a cased photograph, circa 1860 (Box 29, Folder 251)
        Sixth-plate ferrotype; no seal
        Full thermoplastic case with the Nesting Birds motif (Krainik #168); printed on paper lining, "Littlefield, Parson & Co., / MANUFACTURERS OF / Daguerreotype Cases. / L., P. & Co., are the sole / Proprietors and only legal Manu- / facturers of UNION CASES, with the / Embracing Riveted Hinge, / Patented October 14, 1856, / and April 21, 1857."
      - Two tintypes in a case, one depicts a woman, the other a man, circa 1860 (Box 29, Folder 252)
        Sixth-plate tintypes; no seal
        Full double thermoplastic case with Bobby Shafto motif (Krainik #135 and Rinhart #25), c.1857; printed on paper lining, "A.P. CRITCHLOW & CO., / Manufacturers of / Daguerreotype Cases. / A.P.C. & CO. / Are the Original Inventors of / the Composition for the Union Case, / (so called,) including all the various shades / of color and fineness of texture pecu- / liar to their manufacture and of the / EMBRACING RIVETED HINGES, thus / securing them from breaking out as/ do others that are inserted / with or without a / metal brace. / Hinge Patented / OCT. 14, 1856, & APRIL 21, 1857"
      - Two tintypes in a case, each depicting the same woman, circa 1860 (Box 29, Folder 253)
        Sixteenth-plate circle tintypes; unsealed
        Full double-image thermoplastic case with twist-off cover with geometric motif with mother-of-pearl inlay in center
      - Tintype in a case, of a woman, circa 1860 (Box 29, Folder 254)
        Full purple velvet oval case
      - Tintype in a case, of a woman, circa 1860 (Box 29, Folder 255)
        Ninth-plate tintype with additional metal backing plate; unsealed
      - Tintype in a half case, of a woman posed with a bicycle, circa 1860-69 (Box 29, Folder 256)
        Clipping behind the image, probably from the "Literary American" journal, circa 1848-1850
    - Men
      - Daguerreotype in a case, of a man, circa 1849 (Box 29, Folder 257)
        Full leather case with the Tulip and Diamond motif (Rinhart #116)
      - Daguerreotype in a half case, of a man, circa 1850 (Box 29, Folder 258)
      - Daguerreotype in a case, of a man, circa 1850 (Box 29, Folder 259)
        Sixth-plate daguerreotype with a sixteenth-plate oval exposure; original seal
      - Daguerreotype in a case, of a man, circa 1850-55 (Box 29, Folder 260)
        Sixteenth-plate daguerreotype, no seal
      - Daguerreotype in a case, of a man, circa 1850-59 (Box 30, Folder 261)
      - Daguerreotype in a case, of a man, circa 1850-59 (Box 30, Folder 262)
        Full black-lacquer with mother of pearl inlay case, book-style spine with "SOUVENIR" stamp in gold leaf
      - Daguerreotype in pin, of a man, circa 1853 (Box 30, Folder 263)
        1.5 cm x 1.0 cm diameter oval plate daguerreotype
        Gold pin case
      - Daguerreotype in watch case, of a man, circa 1853 (Box 30, Folder 264)
        3.5 cm. diameter plate daguerreotype
        Gold false watch case with places for two daguerreotypes
      - Daguerreotype in a case, of a man, circa 1853 (Box 30, Folder 265)
        Full leather case with Wolfert's Roost motif (Rinhart #17)
      - Daguerreotype in a case, of a man, circa 1854 (Box 30, Folder 266)
        Ninth-plate daguerreotype; unsealed
        Full leather case with the Altar Memorial motif (Rinhart #65)
        Notation repeated three times on verso of image and paper backing, "351 / Miller"
      - Ambrotype in a case, of a man, circa 1855 (Box 30, Folder 267)
        Quarter-plate clear-glass ambrotype with asphaltum/varnish backing; backed with black cloth and cardboard; no seal
        Full brown thermoplastic case with the Capture of Major Andre motif (See Krainik #18); chipped corner; printed on paper lining: "GENUINE UNION CASE, / IMPROVED. / Fine Gilt and Burnish- / ed Hinge. / S. PECK'S PATENT. / Oct. 3d, 1854. / H. HALVORSON'S PATENT, / Aug. 7th, 1855, / Assigned to S. Peck."
      - Ambrotype not in a case, of a man, circa 1855 (Box 30, Folder 268)
        Ninth-plate ruby-glass ambrotype; sealed
      - Daguerreotype in a case, of a man, circa 1855-60 (Box 30, Folder 269)
      - Ambrotype not in a case, of a man, circa 1855-60 (Box 30, Folder 270)
        Quarter-plate hand-tinted ambrotype
      - Ambrotype not in a case, of a man, circa 1855-60 (Box 31, Folder 271)
      - Ambrotype not in a case, of a man, circa 1855-60 (Box 31, Folder 272)
        Ninth-plate ambrotype
      - Ambrotype with no case of a man, circa 1855-60 (Box 31, Folder 273)
      - Tintype in a case, of a man, circa 1856 (Box 31, Folder 274)
        Full black lacquer case with mother of pearl inlay and "MEMENTO" on spine
        Image probably not original to case
      - Daguerreotype in a case, of a man, circa 1856 (Box 31, Folder 275)
        Sixteenth-plate oval daguerreotype
        Half oval velvet case
      - Daguerreotype in a case, of a man holding a flute, circa 1856 (Box 31, Folder 276)
        Sixth-plate daguerreotype; sealed
        Pencil inscription under image, "Found in Tuscon (sic.), Az."
      - Ambrotype in a half case, of a man, circa 1856 (Box 31, Folder 277)
        Sixth-plate ruby-glass ambrotype
      - Ambrotype in a case, of a man, circa 1856 (Box 31, Folder 278)
        Full thermoplastic case with geometric scroll motif; printed in paper backing, "A.P. CRITCHLOW & CO., / Manufacturers of / Daguerreotype Cases. / A.P.C. & CO. / Are the Original Inventors of / the Composition for the Union Case, / (so called,) including all the various shades / of color and fineness of texture pecu- / liar to their manufacture and of the / EMBRACING RIVETED HINGES, thus / securing them from breaking out as / do others that are inserted / with or without a / metal brace. / Hinge Patented / OCT. 14, 1856."
      - Ambrotype in a case, of a man, circa 1856 (Box 31, Folder 279)
        Full leather case with scroll simple motif
      - Ambrotype in a case, of a man, circa 1857 (Box 31, Folder 280)
        Quarter-plate clear-glass ambrotype
        Full leather envelope style case with pink pad
      - Ambrotype not in a case, of a man, circa 1857 (Box 32, Folder 281)
        Quarter-plate clear-glass ambrotype in relievo with metal backing plate; convex cover glass; original seal
      - Ambrotype in a case, of a man, with a woman partially visible on the left edge of the frame, circa 1857 (Box 32, Folder 282)
        Ninth-plate clear-glass ambrotype with black velvet backing; original seal
        Probably a copy photograph
      - Ambrotype in a case, of a man, circa 1857 (Box 32, Folder 283)
        Full leather case with simple floral motif
        Newspaper slip behind image with inscription, "GCH"
      - Ambrotype not in a case, of a man, circa 1857 (Box 32, Folder 284)
        Ninth-plate clear-glass ambrotype with asphaltum/varnish backing; no seal
      - Ambrotype in a case, of a man, circa 1858 (Box 32, Folder 285)
        Full papier-mache case with ornamental circle motif and butterfly motif embossed in velvet pad
      - Ambrotype in a case, postmortem of an elderly man, circa 1858 (Box 32, Folder 286)
      - Ambrotype in a frame, of a man, circa 1858 (Box 32, Folder 287)
        Thermoplastic frame
      - Ambrotype in a case, of a man, probably a fireman, circa 1858 (Box 32, Folder 288)
        Full thermoplastic case with Seated Liberty with Shield motif (Krainik #107); printed on paper lining, "LITTLEFIELD, PARSONS & CO., / Successors to A.P. Critchlow & Co. / MANUFACTURERS OF / Daguerreotype Cases. / L., P. & Co., are the sole / Proprietors and only legal / Manufacturers of / Union Cases, / With the Embracing Riveted Hinge. / Patented / Oct. 14, 1856, & April 21, 1857."
      - Tintype in a case, of a man playing a violin, circa 1858 (Box 32, Folder 289)
        Plate stamped upside on lower edge under mat, "FOR NEFF'S PAT. FEB 56"
        Full papier-mache case with bouquet of flowers motif
      - Ambrotype in a case, of a man, circa 1858-59 (Box 32, Folder 290)